Guide to the Robert Ward Papers, 1910-2012 and undated RL.01344
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert Ward papers
1910-2012 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ward, Robert, 1917-
RL.01344
137 Linear Feet
Robert Ward was a composer primarily of operas, instrumental works, and symphonic choral works. He won the 1962 Pulitzer Prize in Music for his opera, The Crucible, which remains his best-known work. Ward served as Chancellor of the North Carolina School of the Arts and as a faculty member at Columbia and Duke Universities. His papers span from his time as a student at the Eastman School of Music in the 1930s to his final years composing in 2012. They include scores, music sketches, recordings, libretto drafts, correspondence, scrapbooks, research and information files, writings and speeches by and about Ward, as well as concert programs, newspaper clippings, photographs, awards, and other materials that document his professional life and work as a composer.
Access Restrictions
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Contact Research Services for the production of listening or use copies.
The rest of the collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robert Ward Papers was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1998, 2001, 2003, 2010, 2012, 2013, and 2018.
Biographical Note
Robert Ward was a composer primarily of operas, instrumental works, and symphonic choral works. Born in 1917, Ward began composing as a student. He attended the Eastman School of Music and The Juilliard School in the 1930s and early 1940s before joining the United States Army during World War II. During the war he served as a band director, and was stationed in the Pacific. Following the war, Ward taught at Juilliard and Columbia, and continued composing and conducting. His second opera, The Crucible, based on Arthur Miller's play, premiered in 1961 and became his best-known work. He won the Pulitzer Prize in Music for the opera in 1962. Ward eventually left New York and served as Chancellor of the North Carolina School of the Arts from 1967-1975. He joined Duke University as the Mary Duke Biddle Professor of Music in 1979, retiring as Professor Emeritus in 1987. He continued to live and compose in Durham, North Carolina until his death in 2013.
Collection Overview
The Robert Ward Papers have been divided into eight series: Biographical Materials, Correspondence, Operas, Instrumental Works, Vocal Works, Music Sketchbooks and Student Works, Music by Others, and Untitled Recordings. Biographical Materials consists of documents pertaining to Ward's work as a composer, including newspaper clippings, profiles, the composer's published writings and interviews, documents from the organizations with which he affiliated, events held in his honor, and certificates and awards he received. The Correspondence series primarily consists of professional communications between Robert Ward and several organizations. Ward's music has been divided into three series based on genre and arranged alphabetically by title of piece within each series: Operas, Instrumental Works, and Vocal Works. Materials for each composition may include scores, recordings, and publicity materials such as newspaper clippings, programs, and reviews. Music Sketchbooks and Student Works contains assorted untitled music sketches and sketchbooks by Ward, as well as manuscripts for some of his student works. Music by Others includes a variety of scores and recordings by other composers included in Ward's papers, the majority of which are recordings. Untitled Recordings comprises assorted media that contain no composition titles, although some recordings are labeled and dated as specific performances.
Photographs; Composers -- United States -- Correspondence; Audiocassettes; Composers -- United States; Scrapbooks; Scores; Columbia University -- Faculty; North Carolina School of the Arts -- Faculty; Duke University -- Faculty; Opera -- 20th century; Symphonies -- 20th century; Chamber music -- 20th century; Orchestral music -- 20th century; Choruses (Mixed voices), Unaccompanied; Song cycles; Wind ensembles; Overtures (Wind ensemble); Concertos -- 20th century; Overtures; Sacred songs (High voice) with orchestra; Choruses, Sacred (Mixed voices) with organ; Brass band music -- Scores and parts; String quartets -- Scores and parts; Cantatas, Sacred; Compact discs; DVDs; Digital audio tapes; VHS; Malouf, Melissa; Ward, Robert, 1917-; Lang, Daniel; Stambler, Bernard; Duke University. Department of Music
- Biographical Materials, 1939-2010 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical Materials consists of papers pertaining to Robert Ward's professional life as composer. The series includes collected works lists and classifications compiled by both Ward and others; drafts and proofs of Ward's autobiography; biographical profiles, newspaper clippings, assorted event photographs, professional headshots of Ward, and conference and concert programs from throughout his career; details of publishing contracts and commissions for new music; and other publications on his music by Ward himself. Includes documents from the various organizations with which Ward affiliated, including: the Academy of Arts and Letters, the American Musical Theater Project, Friends of the American Musical Theatre, Durham Arts Council, Triangle Opera Theater, Opera Company of North Carolina, and cultural trips to Guatemala and Japan as part of the United States Friendship Commission. Contains materials from the celebrations for his 70th, 80th, and 90th birthdays, including programs, newspaper clippings, contracts, photographs, recordings, and music dedicated to Ward. Recordings include interviews and concert recordings celebrating Ward's music. Includes some materials from Ward's time at Duke Univeristy, such as the concert series Encounters with Music of our Time, the Summer Opera Workshop, and Winterfest. Contains papers and yearbooks from Ward's time as a student at the Eastman School of Music. Includes recordings of several interviews Ward gave throughout his career. Also includes a variety of certificates and awards received by Ward, including degrees, honorary degrees, a key to the city of Raleigh, North Carolina, State of North Carolina medal, and a golden baton from the American Symphony Orchestra League. Grouped and arranged by content type.
  - Robert Ward collected works lists and classifications, 1951-1990 and undated (Box 1)
  - Robert Ward Bibliography Guide, undated (Box 1)
  - Robert Ward: A Bio-Bibliography, a book by Kenneth Kreitner, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Robert Ward: A Bio-Bibliography, proofs, 1988 (Box 1)
    Contains edits and markings
  - Robert Ward biographical papers and notes, undated (Box 1)
    Notes on pieces by Robert Ward, biographical drafts and press releases
  - Robert Ward autobiography drafts, undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
    Individual chapter manuscripts and drafts with edits and notes
  - Robert Ward autobiography edited draft, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Robert Ward autobiography proofs, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Robert Ward autobiography draft, 2003; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Robert Ward interview transcripts, 1982-2005 (Box 1)
  - Certificates and awards, 1918-2007 (Box 1)
  - Honorary degree from Peabody Conservatory, 1975 (Box 1)
    Program, speech notes, press release, newspaper clippings
  - National Endowment for the Arts honoree, 2011; 2 folders (Box 1)
    Programs, newspaper clippings, magazine articles
  - Pultizer Prize in Music award, 1962 (Box 1)
    Correspondence, certificate
  - 70th Birthday Celebration, 1987; 6 folders (Box 2)
    Addresses, letters, correspondence, newspaper clippings, programs, musical piece dedicated to Ward: "Seventy' by Anthony Kelley
  - "Seventy" (Petite Bagatelle #2 for Piano), composed and performed by Anthony Kelley for Robert Ward, 7 October 1987 (Box 20, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0198)
  - 70th Birthday Concert, T.J. Anderson, Boogie Woogie Fantasy by Thomas Warburton, 17 September 1998 (Box 21, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0225)
  - WUNC 70th Birthday Concert and disk interview, undated (Box 17, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0075)
  - 70th Birthday celebration: Lady Kate excerpts, North Carolina Symphony, Charlotte, North Carolina, undated (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0152)
  - Robert Ward 70th Birthday Celebration, Charlotte, North Carolina, 23 September 1987 (Box 15, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0026)
  - 70th Birthday Celebration, North Carolina Symphony, undated (Box 16, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0057)
  - 70th Birthday Celebration poster, 1987 (Box 13)
  - 80th Birthday Celebration, 1997-1998; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Newspaper clippings, programs, student letters
  - 80th Birthday Celebration: Dialogues for Violin, Cello, and Piano; Second Sonata for Violina and Piano; Raleigh Dviertimento; Echoes of America (World Premiere), 14 September 1997 (Box 24, Cd RL01344-CD-0042)
  - Robert Ward: An 80th Birthday Salute, William Ferris Chorale, 20 March 1998 (Box 24, Cd RL01344-CD-0029)
  - 90th Birthday Celebration, 2007-2008 (Box 2)
    Newspaper clippings, programs
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1946-2006; 2 folders (Box 2)
    Newspaper clippings, program, letters, photographs of members
  - Biographical newspaper clippings, 1945-1998; 3 folders (Box 2)
    Includes clippings from the New York Times, Raleigh News & Observer, and Durham Herald-Sun
  - Ceremony and conference programs, 1939-2006; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - American culture program in Guatemala, 1990 (Box 3)
    Newspaper clippings, programs, correspondence, memorandums, photographs
  - Czech National Chamber Orchestra trip, 2001 (Box 3)
    Programs, itinerary, correspondence
  - Japan and United States Frienship Commission, 1983 (Box 3)
    Correspondence, notes
  - A. J. Fletcher Opera Institute, 2002 (Box 3)
    Speech
  - The American Music Theatre, 1997-2001 (Box 3)
    Contracts, budget, support proposal
  - Durham Arts Council production of Carmen, 1985 (Box 3)
    Newspaper clippings, press release, letter
  - Friends of the American Musical Theatre, 1997-2001 and undated (Box 3)
    Correspondence, budget
  - Triangle Opera Theater, 1986-2001 and undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
    Meeting minutes, charter, programs, administrative documents, budgets, by-laws, certificates
  - Opera Company of North Carolina, 2004 (Box 3)
    Meeting minutes
  - Duke University Department of Music, 1980-1986 and undated; 5 folders (Box 3)
    Encounters with Music of Our Time programs, Summer Opera Workshop, Winterfest, Chamber musical theater proposal, booklets
  - Eastman School of Music Douments, 1938-1939; 3 folders (Box 3)
    School papers, yearbooks
  - South Carolina television broadcast, 1997 (Box 3)
    Planning documents, contract negotiations
  - Commission by Oakwood High School Band, 1971-1977 (Box 3)
    Correspondence, programs, contract
  - Funeral arrangements for Mary Ward, 2006 (Box 3)
    Correspondence, programs
  - Pastiche performances, 2001-2002 (Box 3)
  - Music catalogues that include Robert Ward's music, 1978-1991; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Estonian Ballet, a book, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Music is Where you Make it: The Joyful Workings of America's First Youth Orchestra, a book by Jacob Avshalomov, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Dancing Without Walls, a book by Lee Harper (Box 3)
  - Ditson Fund of Columbia University, 2007-2008 (Box 3)
    Meeting minutes, correspondence, proposals
  - Tribute to William Bergsma, undated (Box 3)
    Program, biographical information
  - Assorted music publishing contracts, 1975-2005; 3 folders (Box 4)
    Companies includes ECS, BMI, and Galaxy
  - Guest appearances as keynote speaker or conductor, 1947-2004; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - North Carolina School of the Arts Commencement, 1990 (Box 4)
    Robert Ward's speech, newspaper clipping, program
  - North Carolina School of the Arts brochure, undated (Box 4)
    Includes introduction by Robert Ward
  - Speeches and articles by Robert Ward, 1948-1997; 4 folders (Box 4)
    Speeches and published articles by Robert Ward; includes drafts, notes, outlines, and published versions
  - CD liner notes by Robert Ward, undated (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks, 1948-1956 and undated; 3 folders (Box 4)
    Include newspaper clippings, scrapbook of famous operas, programs, choral score of Hush'd be the Camps Today
  - Letters of Recommendation by Robert Ward, 1980-1997 (Box 4)
  - Assorted notes by Robert Ward, 1963-1971 and undated (Box 4)
    Includes notes on religion, politics, and music lectures
  - Assorted notes by Bernard Stambler and Robert Ward, undated (Box 4)
    Bernard Stambler, librettist of several Robert Ward operas
  - Academic publications on Robert Ward's music, 1958-1995 and undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Biographical profiles of Robert Ward, 1957-2006; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes assorted newsletters
  - Assorted writings by others, 1985-2012 and undated (Box 5)
    Inlcudes articles on music and religion
  - Rev. Arthur C. Ludlow Sermon from Cleveland, OH, 1908 (Box 5)
  - Sarah Johnson press materials, 1991-1997 (Box 5)
    Sarah Johnson, violinist; correspondence, letters of recommendation, photographs
  - Response journals by Gianna Ward-Vetrano, 2001 (Box 5)
    Includes topics on music, religion, and politics
  - Stella Sung promotional packet, 2009 and undated (Box 5)
    Stella Sung, composer; newspaper clippings, programs, photographh
  - Durham Symphony, 1982-1984 (Box 5)
    Programs, reviews of Robert Ward's music
  - CD reviews of Robert Ward's music, 1988-1999 and undated (Box 5)
  - Programs featuring multiple pieces by Robert Ward, 1959-2008; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes concerts dedicated to Robert Ward and the performance of his music
  - Assorted concert programs with no music by Robert Ward, 1950-2008; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Eugene Ormandy autographed photograph, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Studio portraits of Robert Ward, 1973 and undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Assorted event photographs, 1941-1997; 2 folders (Box 5)
    Includes performances of various works by Robert Ward, meetings between Ward and various individuals, including composers, and some family snapshots
  - Assorted diplomas, 1934-1992; 2 folders (Box 12)
    Includes John Adams High School diploma, the Eastman School of Music diploma, The Julliard School, and University of North Carolina Greensboro Doctor of Fine Arts degrees
  - Guest speaker and composer poster, 2003 (Box 12)
    Chamber Music Society of Wilmington
  - Scrapbook, BMI Publishing reception for Robert Ward, 1988 (Box 12)
    Photographs, program
  - Scrapbook, trip to Austria, Hungary, and Germany, 1986-2001 and undated (Box 12)
    Photographs, programs, letters
  - Scrapbook, 1934-1943 (Box 12)
    Newspaper clippings, programs, reviews, photographs, letter
  - Musical America Publication, 1935 (Box 12)
    Includes detailed news of musical life in New York City
  - Assorted posters, 1984-1989 and undated (Box 12)
    Performances of Robert Ward's music
  - Robert Ward conducting portraits, undated (Box 12)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters group photographs, 2006 and undated (Box 13)
  - The Robert Ward Celebration, Honoring the Composer on his 70th Birthday, 1987 (Box 15, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0027)
  - Robert Ward on A Little Night Music, WVIA-FM, 5 March 1995 (Box 15, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0034)
  - The State of Things #110, Opera in North Carolina, WUNC, 20 February 1998, 22 February 1998 (Box 15, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0035)
  - 80th Birthday Concert, undated (Box 16, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0041)
  - 80th Birthday Concert Pre-Concert Talk, 14 September 1997 (Box 16, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0047)
  - Robert Ward interview regarding NCSA, 14 January 1982 (Box 16, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0049)
  - KBS Korea Interview, 26 July 1985 (Box 16, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0051)
  - Korean tape, 15 December 1984 (Box 16, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0052)
  - Robert Ward Feature on Morning Edition, WUNC, 9 August 1988 (Box 16, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0068)
  - RW Bio, 1935, undated (Box 17, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0071)
  - Robert Ward on WQXR, 30 September 1987 (Box 17, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0072)
  - Interview with Robert Ward, Washington D.C., 18 May 1983 (Box 17, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0073)
  - Memorial Service for Samuel Sherwood Benedict, 8 January 2005 (Box 22, Audio-cassette RL01344-CS-0260)
  - North Carolina School of the Arts convocation address, 5 January 1968; 1999 (Box 24, Cd RL01344-CD-0017)
  - Minnesota Public Radio, 1 August 1999 (Box 24, Cd RL01344-CD-0018)
  - Lecture Recital: A Closer Look at Robert Ward, 5 September 2000 (Box 24, Cd RL01344-CD-0035)
  - Robert Ward at NCSSM, 20 September 2006 (Box 25, Cd RL01344-CD-0047)
  - "Far Down the Street," Chapel Choir Christmas Concert, Duke University, conducted by Rodney Wynkoop, undated (Box 25, Cd RL01344-CD-0076)
  - Robert Ward at NCSSM, 20 September 2006 (Box 26, Dvd RL01344-DVD-0015)
  - National Endowment for the Arts honoree video tributes, 2011 (Box 26, Dvd RL01344-DVD-0017)
  - Agnes Albert Hall, 8 April 1999 (Box 27, Video-cassette RL01344-VHS-0013)
  - Bill Friday Interviews Dr. Robert Ward, October 1997 (Box 27, Video-cassette RL01344-VHS-0014)
  - Robert Ward Special, North Carolina People, UNC Center for Public Television, 3 October 1996 (Box 27, Video-cassette RL01344-VHS-0015)
  - Video tape of program for the Music building ground breaking cermony, 3 April 1997 (Box 27, Video-cassette RL01344-VHS-0016)
  - Interview with Dr. WM, 3 October 1997 (Box 27, Video-cassette RL01344-VHS-0026)
  - Interview with Robert Ward, 30 April 1989 (Box 30, Audio-reel RL01344-RR-0007)
    Robert Ward discusses the genesis of The Crucible
  - Speech to National Association of Singing Teachers, undated (Box 31, Audio-reel RL01344-RR-0010)
  - North Carolina School of the Arts plaque to Chancellor Robert and Mary Ward, 1974 (Box 62)
    Signed by the Board of Trustees
  - NCFMC Hinda Honigman Cup, Concerto for Tenor Saxophone, 1991 (Box 83)
  - Greensboro Cultural Center Opening, plaque, 1990 (Box 83)
    "In Recognition of His Contribution to Our American Culture, Robert Ward"
  - Oakwood High School Band and Band Parents Association, decorative plate, 1977 (Box 83)
    Dayton, OH; "With Gratitude and Appreciation"
  - American Symphony Orchestra League, miniature obelisk, 1990 (Box 83)
    "In Recognition of Your Dedicated Support and Commitment to the Quality of Classical Music in America"
  - American Symphony Orchestra League, paperweight, 1989 (Box 83)
    "Robert Ward, In Recognition of Outstanding Contributions to American Orchestras as a Member of the American Symphony Orchestra League Board of Directors, 1977-1989"
  - Pulitzer prize, paperweight, 1991 (Box 83)
    "75th Anniversary, The Pulitzer Prizes, Columbia University"
  - Raleigh News & Observer, pin, undated (Box 83)
    "Tarheel of the Week"
  - Morrison Award, medal, 1983 (Box 83)
    "Presented by the Roanoke Island Historical Association Inc. for Achievement in the Performing Arts"
  - Cleveland Arts Prize in Music, medal, 1972 (Box 83)
  - Miniature Opera House, 1991 (Box 83)
    Painted wooden building cut-out, "Central City Opera House"
  - Key to City of Raleigh, North Carolina, undated (Box 83)
  - Key to Metropolitan Dade County, Florida, undated (Box 83)
  - State of North Carolina Award, medal, 1974 (Box 83)
    "Fine Arts, Achievement is Man's Mark of Greatness"
  - Duke Univeristy Award for Merit, decorative plate, 1987 (Box 83)
  - North Carolina School of the Arts Giannini Society award, 1997 (Box 83)
  - American Symphony Orchestra League Gold Baton Award, 1991 (Box 84)
    Gold-plated baton in case
  - The Contemporary Youth Orchestra, plaque, 1996 (Box 84)
    "With Sincere Appreciation for Sharing Your Talents"
  - Durham Symphony "Sharing the Music Award," plaque, 1997 (Box 84)
  - Durham Arts Council Outstanding Service by an Artist, plaque, 1992 (Box 84)
  - National Opera Association Convention Lifetime Achievement Award, plaque, 1998 (Box 84)
  - Special citation by the Winston Salem Arts Council, 1974 (Box 84)
- Correspondence, 1942-2010 and undated; 2
  Correspondence primarily consists of professional communications between Robert Ward and representatives from several organizations, including: churches, universities, music festivals, opera companies, and symphonies. Organizations include Galaxy Music Corporation, Duke University, North Carolina School of the Arts, Wake Forest University, Minnesota Opera Company, Ohio Light Opera, Brevard Music Center, Chicago Opera Theater, Academy of Arts and Letters, and the Nashville Symphony. The series does include some personal correspondence between Ward and his family and friends. Arranged chronologically by decade.
  - Contents of binder, 1942-1943 (Box 6)
    Correspondence between Robert Ward and his mother
  - General correspondence, 1949-2010 and undated; 9 folders (Box 6)
    Correspondence between Robert Ward and several organizations, including some churches, universities, music festivals, opera companies, and symphonies. Organizations include Duke University, North Carolina School of the Arts, Wake Forest University, Minnesota Opera Company, Ohio Light Opera, Brevard Music Center, Chicago Opera Theater, Academy of Arts and Letters, and the Nashville Symphony. Includes some personal correspondence between Ward and his family and friends.
  - Letters regarding Duke faculty appointments, 1983-1984 (Box 6)
  - Galaxy Music Corporation, 1957-1994 (Box 6)
    Robert Ward, executive vice president and managing editor; official correspondence
  - North Carolina School of the Arts Correspondence, 1967-1998 (Box 6)
    Includes correspondence from Robert Ward's time as Chancellor of the school
  - Rockefeller Grant, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Student letters, 2003 (Box 6)
    Students from Pittsburgh, PA
- Operas, 1956-2012 and undated; 3
  Operas contains a variety of materials related to each of Robert Ward's nine completed operatic works. All of the compositions include an assortment of newspaper clippings, programs, and reviews from their performances. Clippings, programs, and reviews related to The Crucible are by far the most extensive. Almost all the operas have music sketches, libretto drafts, published libretti, piano-vocal scores, orchestral scores, conductor's scores, some individual instrumental parts, and both audio and audiovisual recordings. Media types include audiocassettes, compact discs, digital audio tapes, DVDs, reels, and VHS tapes. The scores include published versions, edited proofs—many in Ward's own hand—master sheets, printing masters, and original manuscripts. Several of the operas also include correspondence from Ward regarding revisions and performances, as well as production photographs, academic publications with musical analyses, set drawings, and stage directions. The materials for Roman Fever include a filming script. The series also includes libretto drafts for an unfinished opera entitled Debs. Recording titles are taken from the media objects themselves. Arranged alphabetically by opera title.
  - Abelard and Heloise, 1977-1984, 1996 and undated; 1
    - Newspaper clippings and programs from premiere at Charlotte Opera, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 7)
      Includes clippings from premiere at Charlotte Opera
    - Correspondence, 1977-1982, 1996 (Box 7)
    - Photographs from Charlotte Opera production, 1982 (Box 7)